<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- lifted from troff+man by doclifter -->
<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en' xml:id='gmtconf5'>




















































<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>GMT.CONF</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>Mar 22 2012</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>GMT 5.0.1b (SVN)</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>gmt.conf</refname>
<refpurpose>Configuration for GMT</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->

<refsect1 xml:id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>The following is a list of the parameters that are user-definable in <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis>.  The
parameter names are always given in UPPER CASE.  The parameter values are
case-insensitive unless otherwise noted.  The
system defaults are given in brackets [ for SI (and US) ].  Those marked <emphasis remap='B'>*</emphasis> can be set on the command
line as well (the corresponding option is given in parentheses).  Note that default distances and
lengths below are given in both cm or inch; the chosen default depends on your choice of default
unit (see <emphasis remap='B'>PROJ_LENGTH_UNIT</emphasis>).  You can explicitly specify the unit used for distances and
lengths by appending <emphasis remap='B'>c</emphasis> (cm), <emphasis remap='B'>i</emphasis> (inch), or <emphasis remap='B'>p</emphasis> (points).
When no unit is indicated the value will be assumed to be in the unit set by <emphasis remap='B'>PROJ_LENGTH_UNIT</emphasis>.
Several parameters take only <emphasis remap='B'>true</emphasis> or <emphasis remap='B'>false</emphasis>.
Finally, most of these parameters can be changed on-the-fly via the <option>--PARAMETER</option>=<emphasis remap='I'>VALUE</emphasis> option to any
<emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis> program.  However, a few are static and are only read via the <emphasis remap='B'>gmt.conf</emphasis> file; these
are labeled (static).</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='common_specifications'><title>COMMON SPECIFICATIONS</title>
<para>The full explanation for how to specify pens, pattern fills, colors, and fonts can be found in the <emphasis remap='B'>gmt</emphasis> man page.</para>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>COLOR_BACKGROUND</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Color used for the background of images (i.e., when z &lt; lowest colortable entry)  [black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>COLOR_FOREGROUND</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Color used for the foreground of images (i.e., when z &gt; highest colortable entry)  [white].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>COLOR_HSV_MAX_SATURATION</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Maximum saturation (0-1) assigned for most positive intensity value [0.1].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>COLOR_HSV_MIN_SATURATION</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Minimum saturation (0-1) assigned for most negative intensity value [1.0].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>COLOR_HSV_MAX_VALUE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Maximum value (0-1) assigned for most positive intensity value [1.0].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>COLOR_HSV_MIN_VALUE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Minimum value (0-1) assigned for most negative intensity value [0.3].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>COLOR_MODEL</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Selects in which color space a color palette should be interpolated.
By default, color interpolation takes place directly on the RGB values which can produce
some unexpected hues, whereas interpolation directly on the HSV values better preserves those hues.
The choices are:
<emphasis remap='B'>none</emphasis> (default: use whatever the COLOR_MODEL setting in the color palette file demands),
<emphasis remap='B'>rgb</emphasis> (force interpolation in RGB),
<emphasis remap='B'>hsv</emphasis> (force interpolation in HSV),
<emphasis remap='B'>cmyk</emphasis> (assumes colors are in CMYK but interpolates in RGB).</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>COLOR_NAN</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Color used for the non-defined areas of images (i.e., where z == NaN)  [127.5].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FONT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets the default for all fonts, except FONT_LOGO. This setting is not included in the <emphasis remap='B'>gmt.conf</emphasis> file.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FONT_ANNOT_PRIMARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Font used for primary annotations, etc. [12p,Helvetica,black]. 
When <emphasis remap='B'>+</emphasis> is prepended, scale fonts, offsets and ticklengths relative to <emphasis remap='B'>FONT_ANNOT_PRIMARY</emphasis>.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FONT_ANNOT_SECONDARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Font to use for time axis secondary annotations [14p,Helvetica,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FONT_LABEL</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Font to use when plotting labels below axes [16p,Helvetica,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FONT_LOGO</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Font to use for text plotted as part of the GMT time logo [8p,Helvetica,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FONT_TITLE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Font to use when plotting titles over graphs [24p,Helvetica,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_CLOCK_IN</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Formatting template that indicates how an input clock string is formatted.  This template
is then used to guide the reading of clock strings in data fields.  To properly decode
12-hour clocks, append am or pm (or upper case) to match your data records. As examples,
try hh:mm, hh:mm:ssAM, etc. [hh:mm:ss].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_CLOCK_MAP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Formatting template that indicates how an output clock string is to be plotted.  This template
is then used to guide the formatting of clock strings in plot annotations.  See <emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_CLOCK_OUT</emphasis>
for details. [hh:mm:ss].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_CLOCK_OUT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Formatting template that indicates how an output clock string is to be formatted.  This template
is then used to guide the writing of clock strings in data fields.  To use a floating point
format for the smallest unit (e.g. seconds), append .xxx, where the number of x indicates
the desired precision.  If no floating point is indicated then the smallest specified unit
will be rounded off to nearest integer.  For 12-hour clocks, append am, AM, a.m., or A.M. (<emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis>
will replace a|A with p|P for pm).  If your template starts with a leading hyphen (-) then each integer item (y,m,d) will be
printed without leading zeros (default uses fixed width formats).  As examples, try
hh:mm, hh.mm.ss, hh:mm:ss.xxxx, hha.m., etc. [hh:mm:ss].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_DATE_IN</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Formatting template that indicates how an input date string is formatted.  This template
is then used to guide the reading of date strings in data fields.  You may specify either
Gregorian calendar format or ISO week calendar format.  Gregorian calendar: Use any
combination of yyyy (or yy for 2-digit years; if so see <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_Y2K_OFFSET_YEAR</emphasis>), mm (or o
for abbreviated month name in the current time language),
and dd, with or without delimiters.  For day-of-year data, use jjj instead of mm and/or dd.
Examples can be ddmmyyyy, yy-mm-dd, dd-o-yyyy, yyyy/dd/mm, yyyy-jjj, etc.
ISO Calendar:  Expected template is yyyy[-]W[-]ww[-]d, where ww is ISO week and d is ISO week
day.  Either template must be consistent, e.g., you cannot specify months if you do not specify
years.  Examples are yyyyWwwd, yyyy-Www, etc. [yyyy-mm-dd].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_DATE_MAP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Formatting template that indicates how an output date string is to be plotted.  This template
is then used to guide the plotting of date strings in data fields.  See <emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_DATE_OUT</emphasis>
for details.  In addition, you may use a single o instead of mm (to plot month name) and
u instead of W[-]ww to plot "Week ##".  Both of these text strings will be affected by
the <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_LANGUAGE</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_TIME_PRIMARY_MAP</emphasis> and <emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_TIME_SECONDARY_MAP</emphasis>
setting.  [yyyy-mm-dd].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_DATE_OUT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Formatting template that indicates how an output date string is to be formatted.  This template
is then used to guide the writing of date strings in data fields.  You may specify either
Gregorian calendar format or ISO week calendar format.  Gregorian calendar: Use any
combination of yyyy (or yy for 2-digit years; if so see <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_Y2K_OFFSET_YEAR</emphasis>), mm (or o for
abbreviated month name in the current time language),
and dd, with or without delimiters.  For day-of-year data, use jjj instead of mm and/or dd.
As examples, try yy/mm/dd, yyyy=jjj, dd-o-yyyy, dd-mm-yy, yy-mm, etc.
ISO Calendar:  Expected template is yyyy[-]W[-]ww[-]d, where ww is ISO week and d is ISO week
day.  Either template must be consistant, e.g., you cannot specify months if you do not specify
years.  As examples, try yyyyWww, yy-W-ww-d, etc. If your template starts with a leading hyphen (-) then each integer item (y,m,d) will be
printed without leading zeros (default uses fixed width formats) [yyyy-mm-dd].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_GEO_MAP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Formatting template that indicates how an output geographical coordinate is to be plotted.  This template
is then used to guide the plotting of geographical coordinates in data fields.  See 
<emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_GEO_OUT</emphasis> for details.  In addition, you can append A which plots the absolute value of 
the coordinate.  The default is ddd:mm:ss.  Not all items may be plotted as this depends on the annotation 
interval.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_GEO_OUT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Formatting template that indicates how an output geographical coordinate is to be formatted.  This template
is then used to guide the writing of geographical coordinates in data fields.  The template is in
general of the form [+|-]D or [+|-]ddd[:mm[:ss]][.xxx][F].  By default, longitudes will be reported in the -180/+180 range.
The various terms have the following purpose:</para>


<para>+	Output longitude in the 0 to 360 range [-180/+180]</para>

<para>-	Output longitude in the -360 to 0 range [-180/+180]</para>

<para>D	Use <emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_FLOAT_OUT</emphasis> for floating point degrees.</para>

<para>ddd	Fixed format integer degrees</para>

<para>:	delimiter used</para>

<para>mm	Fixed format integer arc minutes</para>

<para>ss	Fixed format integer arc seconds</para>

<para>.xxx	Floating fraction of previous integer field, fixed width.</para>

<para>F	Encode sign using WESN suffix</para>

<para>G	Same as F but with a leading space before suffix</para>


<para>The default is D.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_FLOAT_MAP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Format (C language printf syntax) to be used when plotting double precision floating point numbers on maps.
For geographic coordinates, see <emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_GEO_MAP</emphasis>. [%.12lg].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_FLOAT_OUT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Format (C language printf syntax) to be used when printing double precision floating point numbers to output files.
For geographic coordinates, see <emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_GEO_OUT</emphasis>. [%.12lg].  To give some columns a separate format, supply one or
more comma-separated <emphasis remap='I'>cols</emphasis>:<emphasis remap='I'>format</emphasis> specifications, where <emphasis remap='I'>cols</emphasis> can be specific columns (e.g., 5 for 6th since 0 is the first)
or a range of columns (e.g., 3-7).  The last specification without column information will override the format
for all other columns.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_TIME_LOGO</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Defines the format of the time information in the UNIX time stamp. This format is parsed by the C function <emphasis remap='B'>strftime</emphasis>,
so that virtually any text can be used (even not containing any time information)  [%Y %b %d %H:%M:%S].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_TIME_PRIMARY_MAP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Controls how primary month-, week-, and weekday-names are formatted.  Choose among full, abbreviated, and
character.  If the leading f, a, or c are replaced with F, A, and C the entire annotation will be in upper case  [full].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_TIME_SECONDARY_MAP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Controls how secondary month-, week-, and weekday-names are formatted.  Choose among full, abbreviated, and
character.  If the leading f, a, or c are replaced with F, A, and C the entire annotation will be in upper case  [full].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>GMT_FFT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines which Fast Fourier Transform should be used among those that have been configured during installation.
Choose from auto (pick the most suitable for the task among available algorithms), brenner (GMT's version of Normal Brenner's
Fortran multi-dimensional FFT), fftw (The Fastest Fourier Transform in the West), accelerate (Use the Accelerate Framework under OS X), fftpack
(use Paul N. Swarztrauber FFT pack translated from Fortran) or perflib (Sun Performance Library under Solaris) [auto].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>GMT_HISTORY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>If true, passes the history of past common command options via the hidden .gmtcommands file [true].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>GMT_INTERPOLANT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines if linear (linear), Akima's spline (akima), natural cubic spline (cubic) or\"'
no interpolation (none) should be used for 1-D interpolations in various programs [akima].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>GMT_TRIANGULATE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines if we use the <emphasis remap='B'>Watson</emphasis> [Default] or <emphasis remap='B'>Shewchuk</emphasis> algorithm (if configured during installation) for triangulation.
Note that Shewchuk is required for operations involving Voronoi constructions.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>GMT_VERBOSE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -V</emphasis>) Determines the level of verbosity used by <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis> programs.  Choose among 5 levels; each level
adds to the verbosity of the lower levels: 0 = silence, 1 = fatal errors, 2 = warnings and progress reports,
3 = extensive progress reports, 4 = debugging messages  [1].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>IO_COL_SEPARATOR</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>This setting determines what character will separate ASCII output data columns written by <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis>.  Choose
from tab, space, comma, and none [tab].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>IO_GRIDFILE_FORMAT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Default file format for grids, with optional scale, offset and invalid value, written as
<emphasis remap='I'>ff</emphasis>/<emphasis remap='I'>scale</emphasis>/<emphasis remap='I'>offset</emphasis>/<emphasis remap='I'>invalid</emphasis>. The 2-letter format indicator can be one of [<emphasis remap='B'>bcnsr</emphasis>][<emphasis remap='B'>bsifd</emphasis>]. The first
letter indicates native <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis> binary, old format netCDF, COARDS-compliant netCDF, Surfer format or Sun
Raster format. The second letter stands for byte, short, int, float and double, respectively. When
/<emphasis remap='I'>invalid</emphasis> is omitted the appropriate value for the given format is used (NaN or largest negative).
When /<emphasis remap='I'>scale</emphasis>/<emphasis remap='I'>offset</emphasis> is omitted, /1.0/0.0 is used. [nf].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>IO_GRIDFILE_SHORTHAND</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>If true, all grid file names are examined to see if they use the file extension
shorthand discussed in Section 4.17 of the <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis> Technical Reference and Cookbook.
If false, no filename expansion is done [false].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>IO_HEADER</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -H</emphasis>) Specifies whether input/output ASCII files have header record(s) or not  [false].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>IO_LONLAT_TOGGLE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -:</emphasis>) Set if the first two columns of input and output files contain (latitude,longitude) or (y,x) rather than the expected
(longitude,latitude) or (x,y).  false means we have (x,y) both on input and output.  true means both input and output
should be (y,x).  IN means only input has (y,x), while OUT means only output should be (y,x).  [false].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>IO_N_HEADER_RECS</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specifies how many header records to expect if <option>-h</option> is used  [1].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>IO_NAN_RECORDS</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines what happens when input records containing NaNs for <emphasis remap='I'>x</emphasis> or <emphasis remap='I'>y</emphasis> (and in some
cases <emphasis remap='I'>z</emphasis>) are read.  Choose between <emphasis remap='B'>skip</emphasis>, which will simply report how many bad
records were skipped, and <emphasis remap='B'>pass</emphasis> [Default], which will pass these records on to the calling programs.
For most programs this will result in output records with NaNs as well, but some will interpret these
NaN records to indicate gaps in a series; programs may then use that information to detect segmentation (if
applicable).</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>IO_SEGMENT_MARKER</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>This holds the character we expect to indicate a segment header in an incoming ASCII data or text table  [&gt;].  If this
marker should be different for output then append another character for the output segment marker.  The two
characters must be separated by a comma.  Two marker characters have special meaning: B means "blank line" and
will treat blank lines as initiating a new segment, whereas N means "NaN record" and will treat records with
all NaNs as initiating a new segment.  If you choose B or N for the output marker then the normal GMT segment
header is replaced by a blank or NaN record, respectively, and no segment header information is written. To use B or N as regular segment markers you must escape them with a leading backslash.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_ANNOT_MIN_ANGLE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>If the angle between the map boundary and the annotation baseline is less than this minimum value (in degrees), the
annotation is not plotted (this may occur for certain oblique projections.)  Give a value in the
range 0-90. [20]</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_ANNOT_MIN_SPACING</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>If an annotation would be plotted less than this minimum distance from its closest neighbor, the
annotation is not plotted (this may occur for certain oblique projections.) [0p]</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_ANNOT_OBLIQUE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>This integer is a sum of 6 bit flags (most of which only are relevant for oblique projections):
If bit 1 is set (1), annotations will occur wherever a gridline crosses the
map boundaries, else longitudes will be annotated on the lower and upper boundaries only, and latitudes will be
annotated on the left and right boundaries only.  If bit 2 is set (2), then longitude annotations will
be plotted horizontally.  If bit 3 is set (4), then latitude annotations will be plotted horizontally.
If bit 4 is set (8), then oblique tickmarks are extended to give a projection equal to the specified tick length.
If bit 5 is set (16), tickmarks will be drawn normal to the border regardless of gridline angle.
If bit 6 is set (32), then latitude annotations will be plotted parallel to the border.
To set a combination of these, add up the values in parentheses. [1].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_ANNOT_OFFSET_PRIMARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Distance from end of tickmark to start of annotation [5p].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_ANNOT_OFFSET_SECONDARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Distance from base of primary annotation to the top of the secondary annotation [5p] (Only
applies to time axes with both primary and secondary annotations).</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_ANNOT_ORTHO</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines which axes will get their annotations (for linear projections) plotted orthogonally to the axes.
Combine any <emphasis remap='B'>w</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>e</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>s</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>n</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>z</emphasis> (uppercase allowed as well). [we].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_DEFAULT_PEN</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets the default of all pens related to <option>-W</option> options. Prepend <emphasis remap='B'>+</emphasis> to overrule the color of the
parameters <emphasis remap='B'>MAP_GRID_PEN_PRIMARY</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>MAP_GRID_PEN_SECONDARY</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>MAP_FRAME_PEN</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>MAP_TICK_PEN_PRIMARY</emphasis>, and <emphasis remap='B'>MAP_TICK_PEN_SECONDARY</emphasis>
by the color of <emphasis remap='B'>MAP_DEFAULT_PEN</emphasis>  [default,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_DEGREE_SYMBOL</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines what symbol is used to plot the degree symbol on geographic map annotations.  Choose between
ring, degree, colon, or none [ring].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_FRAME_AXES</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets which axes to draw and annotate.  Combine any uppercase <emphasis remap='B'>W</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>E</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>S</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>N</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>Z</emphasis> to draw and annotate
west, east, south, north and/or vertical (perspective view only) axis.  Use lower case to draw the axis only, but not annotate.
Add an optional <emphasis remap='B'>+</emphasis> to draw a cube of axes in perspective view.
[WESN].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_FRAME_PEN</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Pen attributes used to draw plain map frame [thicker,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_FRAME_TYPE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Choose between <emphasis remap='B'>inside</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>plain</emphasis> and <emphasis remap='B'>fancy</emphasis> (thick boundary, alternating black/white frame; append <emphasis remap='B'>+</emphasis> for rounded corners)  [fancy].
For some map projections (e.g., Oblique Mercator), plain is the only option even if fancy is set as default.
In general, fancy only applies to situations where the projected x and y directions parallel the lon and lat
directions (e.g., rectangular projections, polar projections).  For situations where all boundary ticks and annotations
must be inside the maps (e.g., for preparing geotiffs), chose <emphasis remap='B'>inside</emphasis>.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_FRAME_WIDTH</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Width (&gt; 0) of map borders for fancy map frame [5p].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_GRID_CROSS_SIZE_PRIMARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Size (&gt;= 0) of grid cross at lon-lat intersections.  0 means draw continuous gridlines
instead [0p].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_GRID_CROSS_SIZE_SECONDARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Size (&gt;= 0) of grid cross at secondary lon-lat intersections.  0 means draw continuous gridlines
instead [0p].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_GRID_PEN_PRIMARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Pen attributes used to draw primary grid lines in dpi units or points (append p) [default,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_GRID_PEN_SECONDARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Pen attributes used to draw secondary grid lines in dpi units or points (append p) [thinner,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_LABEL_OFFSET</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Distance from base of axis annotations to the top of the axis label [8p].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_LINE_STEP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines the maximum length (&gt; 0) of individual straight line-segments when drawing arcuate lines  [0.75p]</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_LOGO</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -U</emphasis>) Specifies if a GMT logo with system timestamp should be plotted
at the lower left corner of the plot  [false].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_LOGO_POS</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -U</emphasis>) Sets the justification and the position of the logo/timestamp box relative to the current plots lower left corner
of the plot  [BL/-54p/-54p].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_ORIGIN_X</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -X</emphasis>) Sets the x-coordinate of the origin on the paper for a new plot [1i].
For an overlay, the default offset is 0i.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_ORIGIN_Y</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -Y</emphasis>) Sets the y-coordinate of the origin on the paper for a new plot [1i].
For an overlay, the default offset is 0i.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_POLAR_CAP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Controls the appearance of gridlines near the poles for all azimuthal projections and a few others in which
the geographic poles are plotted as points (Lambert Conic, Hammer, Mollweide, Sinusoidal, and van der Grinten).  Specify either none (in which
case there is no special handling) or <emphasis remap='I'>pc_lat</emphasis>/<emphasis remap='I'>pc_dlon</emphasis>.  In that case, normal gridlines are only drawn between
the latitudes -<emphasis remap='I'>pc_lat</emphasis>/+<emphasis remap='I'>pc_lat</emphasis>, and above those latitudes the gridlines are spaced at the (presumably coarser)
<emphasis remap='I'>pc_dlon</emphasis> interval; the two domains are separated by a small circle drawn at the <emphasis remap='I'>pc_lat</emphasis> latitude [85/90].
Note for r-theta (polar) projection where r = 0 is at the center of the plot the meaning of the cap is reversed, i.e.,
the default 85/90 will draw a r = 5 radius circle at the center of the map with less frequent radial lines there.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_SCALE_HEIGHT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets the height (&gt; 0) on the map of the map scale bars drawn by various programs [5p].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_TICK_LENGTH_PRIMARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>The length of a primary major/minor tickmarks  [5p/2.5p].
If only the first value is set, the second is assumed to be 50% of the first.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_TICK_LENGTH_SECONDARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>The length of a secondary major/minor tickmarks  [15p/3.75p].
If only the first value is set, the second is assumed to be 25% of the first.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_TICK_PEN_PRIMARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Pen attributes to be used for primary tickmarks in dpi units or points (append p) [thinner,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_TICK_PEN_SECONDARY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Pen attributes to be used for secondary tickmarks in dpi units or points (append p) [thinner,black].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_TITLE_OFFSET</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Distance from top of axis annotations (or axis label, if present) to base of plot title [14p].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>MAP_VECTOR_SHAPE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines the shape of the head of a vector.   Normally (i.e., for vector_shape = 0),
the head will be triangular, but can be changed to an arrow (1) or an open V (2).
Intermediate settings give something in between. Negative values (up to -2) are allowed as well  [0].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PROJ_ELLIPSOID</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>The (case sensitive) name of the ellipsoid used for the map projections  [WGS-84].  Choose among:</para>

<para>Airy: Applies to Great Britain (1830)</para>

<para>Airy-Ireland: Applies to Ireland in 1965 (1830)</para>

<para>Andrae: Applies to Denmark and Iceland (1876)</para>

<para>APL4.9: Appl. Physics (1965)</para>

<para>ATS77: Average Terrestrial System, Canada Maritime provinces (1977)</para>

<para>Australian: Applies to Australia (1965)</para>

<para>Bessel: Applies to Central Europe, Chile, Indonesia (1841)</para>

<para>Bessel-Namibia: Same as Bessel-Schwazeck (1841)</para>

<para>Bessel-NGO1948: Modified Bessel for NGO 1948 (1841)</para>

<para>Bessel-Schwazeck: Applies to Namibia (1841)</para>

<para>Clarke-1858: Clarke's early ellipsoid (1858)</para>

<para>Clarke-1866: Applies to North America, the Philippines (1866)</para>

<para>Clarke-1866-Michigan: Modified Clarke-1866 for Michigan (1866)</para>

<para>Clarke-1880: Applies to most of Africa, France (1880)</para>

<para>Clarke-1880-Arc1950: Modified Clarke-1880 for Arc 1950 (1880)</para>

<para>Clarke-1880-IGN: Modified Clarke-1880 for IGN (1880)</para>

<para>Clarke-1880-Jamaica: Modified Clarke-1880 for Jamaica (1880)</para>

<para>Clarke-1880-Merchich: Modified Clarke-1880 for Merchich (1880)</para>

<para>Clarke-1880-Palestine: Modified Clarke-1880 for Palestine (1880)</para>

<para>CPM : Comm. des Poids et Mesures, France (1799)</para>

<para>Delambre: Applies to Belgium (1810)</para>

<para>Engelis: Goddard Earth Models (1985)</para>

<para>Everest-1830: India, Burma, Pakistan, Afghanistan, Thailand (1830)</para>

<para>Everest-1830-Kalianpur: Modified Everest for Kalianpur (1956) (1830)</para>

<para>Everest-1830-Kertau: Modified Everest for Kertau, Malaysia &amp; Singapore (1830)</para>

<para>Everest-1830-Pakistan: Modified Everest for Pakistan (1830)</para>

<para>Everest-1830-Timbalai: Modified Everest for Timbalai, Sabah Sarawak (1830)</para>

<para>Fischer-1960: Used by NASA for Mercury program (1960)</para>

<para>Fischer-1960-SouthAsia: Same as Modified-Fischer-1960 (1960)</para>

<para>Fischer-1968: Used by NASA for Mercury program (1968)</para>

<para>FlatEarth: As Sphere, but implies fast "Flat Earth" distance calculations (1984)</para>

<para>GRS-67: International Geodetic Reference System (1967)</para>

<para>GRS-80: International Geodetic Reference System (1980)</para>

<para>Hayford-1909: Same as the International 1924 (1909)</para>

<para>Helmert-1906: Applies to Egypt (1906)</para>

<para>Hough: Applies to the Marshall Islands (1960)</para>

<para>Hughes-1980: Hughes Aircraft Company for DMSP SSM/I grid products (1980)</para>

<para>IAG-75: International Association of Geodesy (1975)</para>

<para>Indonesian: Applies to Indonesia (1974)</para>

<para>International-1924: Worldwide use (1924)</para>

<para>International-1967: Worldwide use (1967)</para>

<para>Kaula: From satellite tracking (1961)</para>

<para>Krassovsky: Used in the (now former) Soviet Union (1940)</para>

<para>Lerch: For geoid modelling (1979)</para>

<para>Maupertius: Really old ellipsoid used in France (1738)</para>

<para>Mercury-1960: Same as Fischer-1960 (1960)</para>

<para>MERIT-83: United States Naval Observatory (1983)</para>

<para>Modified-Airy: Same as Airy-Ireland (1830)</para>

<para>Modified-Fischer-1960: Applies to Singapore (1960)</para>

<para>Modified-Mercury-1968: Same as Fischer-1968 (1968)</para>

<para>NWL-10D: Naval Weapons Lab (Same as WGS-72) (1972)</para>

<para>NWL-9D: Naval Weapons Lab (Same as WGS-66) (1966)</para>

<para>OSU86F: Ohio State University (1986)</para>

<para>OSU91A: Ohio State University (1991)</para>

<para>Plessis: Old ellipsoid used in France (1817)</para>

<para>SGS-85: Soviet Geodetic System (1985)</para>

<para>South-American: Applies to South America (1969)</para>

<para>Sphere: The mean radius in WGS-84 (for spherical/plate tectonics applications) (1984)</para>

<para>Struve: Friedrich Georg Wilhelm Struve (1860)</para>

<para>TOPEX: Used commonly for altimetry (1990)</para>

<para>Walbeck: First least squares solution by Finnish astronomer (1819)</para>

<para>War-Office: Developed by G. T. McCaw (1926)</para>

<para>WGS-60: World Geodetic System (1960)</para>

<para>WGS-66: World Geodetic System (1966)</para>

<para>WGS-72: World Geodetic System (1972)</para>

<para>WGS-84: World Geodetic System [Default] (1984)</para>

<para>Moon: Moon (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Mercury: Mercury (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Venus: Venus (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Mars: Mars (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Jupiter: Jupiter (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Saturn: Saturn (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Uranus: Uranus (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Neptune: Neptune (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Pluto: Pluto (IAU2000) (2000)</para>

<para>Note that for some global projections, <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis> may use a spherical approximation of the
ellipsoid chosen, setting the flattening to zero, and using a mean radius.
A warning will be given when this happens.
If a different
ellipsoid name than those mentioned here is given, <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis> will attempt to parse the
name to extract the semi-major axis (<emphasis remap='I'>a</emphasis> in m) and the flattening. Formats allowed are:</para>


<para>	<emphasis remap='I'>a</emphasis>		implies a zero flattening</para>

<para>	<emphasis remap='I'>a</emphasis>,<emphasis remap='I'>inv_f</emphasis>	where <emphasis remap='I'>inv_f</emphasis> is the inverse flattening</para>

<para>	<emphasis remap='I'>a</emphasis>,<emphasis remap='B'>b=</emphasis><emphasis remap='I'>b</emphasis>	where <emphasis remap='I'>b</emphasis> is the semi-minor axis (in m)</para>

<para>	<emphasis remap='I'>a</emphasis>,<emphasis remap='B'>f=</emphasis><emphasis remap='I'>f</emphasis>	where <emphasis remap='I'>f</emphasis> is the flattening</para>


<para>This way a
custom ellipsoid (e.g., those used for other planets) may be used. Further note that coordinate
transformations in <emphasis remap='B'>mapproject</emphasis> can also specify specific datums; see the <emphasis remap='B'>mapproject</emphasis>
man page for further details and how to view ellipsoid and datum parameters.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PROJ_LENGTH_UNIT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets the unit length.  Choose between <emphasis remap='B'>c</emphasis>m, <emphasis remap='B'>i</emphasis>nch, or <emphasis remap='B'>p</emphasis>oint  [c (or i)].  Note
that, in <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis>, one point is defined as 1/72 inch (the <emphasis remap='I'>PostScript</emphasis> definition), while it
is often defined as 1/72.27 inch in the typesetting industry.  There is no universal definition.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PROJ_SCALE_FACTOR</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Changes the default map scale factor used for the Polar Stereographic [0.9996], UTM [0.9996], and Transverse Mercator [1] projections
in order to minimize areal distortion.  Provide a new scale-factor or leave as default.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_CHAR_ENCODING</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(static) Names the eight bit character set being used for text in files and in command line parameters. This allows <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis>
to ensure that the <emphasis remap='I'>PostScript</emphasis> output generates the correct characters on the plot..  Choose from Standard, Standard+, ISOLatin1, ISOLatin1+,
and ISO-8859-x (where x is in the ranges 1-10 or 13-15).  See Appendix F for details [ISOLatin1+ (or Standard+)].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_COLOR_MODEL</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines whether <emphasis remap='I'>PostScript</emphasis> output should use RGB, HSV, CMYK, or GRAY when specifying color [rgb].
Note if HSV is selected it does not apply to images which in that case uses RGB. When selecting GRAY, all
colors will be converted to gray scale using YIQ (television) conversion.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_COMMENTS</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(static) If true we will issue comments in the <emphasis remap='I'>PostScript</emphasis> file that explain the logic of operations.
These are useful if you need to edit the file and make changes; otherwise you can set it to
false which yields a somewhat slimmer <emphasis remap='I'>PostScript</emphasis> file [false].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_COPIES</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -c</emphasis>) Number of plot copies to make  [1].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_IMAGE_COMPRESS</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(static) Determines if <emphasis remap='I'>PostScript</emphasis> images are compressed using the Run-Length Encoding scheme (rle),
Lempel-Ziv-Welch compression (lzw), or not at all (none) [lzw].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_LINE_CAP</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines how the ends of a line segment will be drawn.  Choose among a <emphasis remap='I'>butt</emphasis> cap (default)
where there is no projection beyond the end of the path, a <emphasis remap='I'>round</emphasis> cap where a
semicircular arc with diameter equal to the linewidth is drawn around the end points,
and <emphasis remap='I'>square</emphasis> cap where a half square of size equal to the linewidth extends beyond
the end of the path [butt].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_LINE_JOIN</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines what happens at kinks in line segments.  Choose among a <emphasis remap='I'>miter</emphasis> join
where the outer edges of the strokes for the two segments are extended until they
meet at an angle (as in a picture frame; if the angle is too acute, a bevel join is used
instead, with threshold set by <emphasis remap='B'>PS_MITER_LIMIT</emphasis>), <emphasis remap='I'>round</emphasis> join where a
circular arc is used to fill in the cracks at the kinks, and <emphasis remap='I'>bevel</emphasis> join which
is a miter join that is cut off so kinks are triangular in shape [miter].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_MEDIA</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets the physical format of the current plot paper [a4 (or letter)].  The following
formats (and their widths and heights in points) are recognized (Additional
site-specific formats may be specified in
the gmt_custom_media.conf file in <emphasis remap='B'>$GMT_SHAREDIR</emphasis>/conf or ~/.gmt; see that file for details):</para>


<para>Media	width	height</para>

<para>A0	2380	3368</para>

<para>A1	1684	2380</para>

<para>A2	1190	1684</para>

<para>A3	842	1190</para>

<para>A4	595	842</para>

<para>A5	421	595</para>

<para>A6	297	421</para>

<para>A7	210	297</para>

<para>A8	148	210</para>

<para>A9	105	148</para>

<para>A10	74	105</para>

<para>B0	2836	4008</para>

<para>B1	2004	2836</para>

<para>B2	1418	2004</para>

<para>B3	1002	1418</para>

<para>B4	709	1002</para>

<para>B5	501	709</para>

<para>archA	648	864</para>

<para>archB	864	1296</para>

<para>archC	1296	1728</para>

<para>archD	1728	2592</para>

<para>archE	2592	3456</para>

<para>flsa	612	936</para>

<para>halfletter	396	612</para>

<para>statement	396	612</para>

<para>note	540	720</para>

<para>letter	612	792</para>

<para>legal	612	1008</para>

<para>11x17	792	1224</para>

<para>tabloid	792	1224</para>

<para>ledger	1224	792</para>


<para>For a completely custom format (e.g., for large format plotters) you may also
specify WxH, where W and H are in points unless you append a unit
to each dimension (<emphasis remap='B'>c</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>i</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='B'>m</emphasis> or <emphasis remap='B'>p</emphasis> [Default]).</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_MITER_LIMIT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets the threshold angle in degrees (integer in 0-180 range) used for mitered joins only.
When the angle between joining line segments is smaller than the threshold the corner will
be bevelled instead of mitered.
The default threshold is 35 degrees.
Setting the threshold angle to 0 implies the <emphasis remap='I'>PostScript</emphasis> default of about 11 degrees.
Setting the threshold angle to 180 causes all joins to be beveled.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_PAGE_COLOR</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets the color of the imaging background, i.e., the paper  [white].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_PAGE_ORIENTATION</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(<emphasis remap='B'>* -P</emphasis>) Sets the orientation of the page.  Choose portrait or landscape  [landscape].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_SCALE_X</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Global x-scale (&gt; 0) to apply to plot-coordinates before plotting.  Normally used to shrink
the entire output down to fit a specific height/width  [1.0].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_SCALE_Y</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Global y-scale (&gt; 0) to apply to plot-coordinates before plotting.  Normally used to shrink
the entire output down to fit a specific height/width  [1.0].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>PS_TRANSPARENCY</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Sets the transparency mode to use when preparing PS for rendering to PDF.
Choose from Color, ColorBurn, ColorDodge, Darken, Difference, Exclusion, HardLight, Hue,
Lighten, Luminosity, Multiply, Normal, Overlay, Saturation, SoftLight, and Screen [Normal].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_EPOCH</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specifies the value of the calendar and clock at the origin (zero point) of relative time units (see <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_UNIT</emphasis>).
It is a string of the form yyyy-mm-ddT[hh:mm:ss] (Gregorian) or yyyy-Www-ddT[hh:mm:ss] (ISO)
Default is 2000-01-01T12:00:00, the epoch of the J2000 system.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_INTERVAL_FRACTION</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Determines if partial intervals at the start and end of an axis should be annotated.  If the range of the partial
interval exceeds the specified fraction of the normal interval stride we will place the annotation centered on the
partial interval  [0.5].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_IS_INTERVAL</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Used when input calendar data should be truncated and adjusted to the middle of the relevant interval.
In the following discussion, the unit <emphasis remap='B'>u</emphasis> can be one of these time units: (<emphasis remap='B'>y</emphasis> year, <emphasis remap='B'>o</emphasis> month,
<emphasis remap='B'>u</emphasis> ISO week, <emphasis remap='B'>d</emphasis> day, <emphasis remap='B'>h</emphasis> hour, <emphasis remap='B'>m</emphasis> minute, and <emphasis remap='B'>s</emphasis> second).  <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_IS_INTERVAL</emphasis>
can have any of the following three values: (1) OFF [Default].  No adjustment, time is decoded as given.
(2) +<emphasis remap='I'>n</emphasis><emphasis remap='B'>u</emphasis>.  Activate interval adjustment for input by truncate to previous whole number of <emphasis remap='I'>n</emphasis>
units and then center time on the following interval.  (3) -<emphasis remap='I'>n</emphasis><emphasis remap='B'>u</emphasis>.  Same, but center time on the
previous interval.  For example, with <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_IS_INTERVAL</emphasis> = +1o, an input data string like 1999-12 will
be interpreted to mean 1999-12-15T12:00:00.0 (exactly middle of December), while if <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_IS_INTERVAL</emphasis> = off
then that date is interpreted to mean 1999-12-01T00:00:00.0 (start of December)  [off].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_LANGUAGE</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Language to use when plotting calendar items such as months and days.  Select from:</para>

<para>BR	Brazilian Portuguese</para>

<para>CN1	Simplified Chinese</para>

<para>CN2	Traditional Chinese</para>

<para>DE	German</para>

<para>DK	Danish</para>

<para>EH	Basque</para>

<para>ES	Spanish</para>

<para>FI	Finnish</para>

<para>FR	French</para>

<para>GR	Greek</para>

<para>HI	Hawaiian</para>

<para>HU	Hungarian</para>

<para>IE	Irish</para>

<para>IL	Hebrew</para>

<para>IS	Icelandic</para>

<para>IT	Italian</para>

<para>JP	Japanese</para>

<para>NL	Dutch</para>

<para>NO	Norwegian</para>

<para>PL	Polish</para>

<para>PT	Portuguese</para>

<para>RU	Russian</para>

<para>SE	Swedish</para>

<para>SG	Scottish Gaelic</para>

<para>TO	Tongan</para>

<para>TR	Turkish</para>

<para>UK	British English</para>

<para>US	US English</para>


<para>If your language is not supported, please examine the <emphasis remap='B'>$GMT_SHAREDIR</emphasis>/time/us.d file and
make a similar file.  Please submit it to the <emphasis remap='B'>GMT</emphasis> Developers for official inclusion. 
Custom language files can be placed in directories <emphasis remap='B'>$GMT_SHAREDIR</emphasis>/time or ~/.gmt.
Note: Some of these languages may require you to also change the <emphasis remap='B'>PS_CHAR_ENCODING</emphasis> setting.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_SYSTEM</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Shorthand for a combination of <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_EPOCH</emphasis> and <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_UNIT</emphasis>, specifying
which time epoch the relative time refers to and what the units are.
Choose from one of the preset systems below (epoch and units are indicated):</para>

<para>JD	-4713-11-25T12:00:00	d	(Julian Date)</para>

<para>MJD	1858-11-27T00:00:00	d	(Modified Julian Date)</para>

<para>J2000	2000-01-01T12:00:00	d	(Astronomical time)</para>

<para>S1985	1985-01-01T00:00:00	s	(Altimetric time)</para>

<para>UNIX	1970-01-01T00:00:00	s	(UNIX time)</para>

<para>RD0001	0001-01-01T00:00:00	s</para>

<para>RATA	0000-12-31T00:00:00	d</para>

<para>This parameter is not stored in the <emphasis remap='B'>gmt.conf</emphasis> file but is translated to the respective
values of <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_EPOCH</emphasis> and <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_UNIT</emphasis>.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_EPOCH</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specifies the epoch for relative time  [2000-01-01T12:00:00].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_UNIT</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specifies the units of relative time data since epoch (see <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_EPOCH</emphasis>).
Choose y (year - assumes all years are 365.2425 days), o (month - assumes
all months are of equal length y/12), d (day), h (hour), m (minute), or s (second)  [d].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_WEEK_START</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>When weeks are indicated on time axes, this parameter determines the first day of the week
for Gregorian calendars.  (The ISO weekly calendar always begins weeks with Monday.)
[Sunday].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>TIME_Y2K_OFFSET_YEAR</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>When 2-digit years are used to represent 4-digit years (see various <emphasis remap='B'>FORMAT_DATE</emphasis>s), <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_Y2K_OFFSET_YEAR</emphasis> 
gives the first year in a 100-year sequence.  For example, if <emphasis remap='B'>TIME_Y2K_OFFSET_YEAR</emphasis> is 1729, then numbers 
29 through 99 correspond to 1729 through 1799, while numbers 00 through 28 correspond to 1800 through 
1828. [1950].</para>

  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para><citerefentry><refentrytitle>gmt</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gmtdefaults</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gmtcolors</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gmtget</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gmtset</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

