<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- lifted from troff+man by doclifter -->
<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en' xml:id='mgd77sniffer1'>




















































<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>MGD77SNIFFER</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>Mar 22 2012</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>GMT 5.0.1b (SVN)</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>mgd77sniffer</refname>
<refpurpose>Along-track quality control of MGD77 cruises</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id='synopsis'>
<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>mgd77sniffer</command>    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>NGDC-ids</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-Afieldabbrev,scale,offset </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-Cmaxspd </arg>
    <group choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>-Dd </arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>e</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>E</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>f</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>l</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>m</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>s</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>v</replaceable></arg><arg choice='opt'><replaceable>r</replaceable></arg></group>
    <arg choice='opt'>-gfieldabbrev,imggrid,scale,mode </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-Gfieldabbrev,grid </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-H </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-Ifieldabbrev,rec1,recN </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-K </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-Lcustom-limits-file </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-N </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>-Rwest/east/south/north </arg><arg choice='opt'><replaceable>r</replaceable></arg></arg>
    <group choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>-Sd </arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>s</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>t</replaceable></arg></group>
    <arg choice='opt'>-Tgap </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>-V </arg><arg choice='opt'><replaceable>level</replaceable></arg></arg>
    <group choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>-Wc </arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>g</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>o</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>s</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>t</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>v</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>x</replaceable></arg></group>
    <arg choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>-bo </arg><arg choice='opt'><replaceable>t</replaceable></arg></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>-n </arg><arg choice='opt'>+tthreshold </arg></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsect1 xml:id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para><command>mgd77sniffer</command> scans old (pre-Y2K) and new format ASCII MGD77 files for errors using point-by-point
sanity checking, along-track detection of excessive slopes, and optional comparison of
cruise data with global gravity and predicted bathymetry grids. Detected data problems are output
by default as verbose descriptions of each detected error, often resulting in multiple messages per 
scanned record. Data problems are optionally output (<option>-De</option> option) using a computer-parseable format
(see E77 ERROR FORMAT description below). Default error thresholds are derived from histograms of
all MGD77 geophysical data collected between 1952 and January, 2006. Thresholds are adjustable with
the <option>-L</option> option.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='requirements'><title>REQUIREMENTS</title>
<para>The mgd77sniffer links with Generic Mapping Tools 4.0 or later along with the supplemental GMT
packages x2sys and mgd77. See http://gmt.soest.hawaii.edu for GMT details. Grids for comparison with
cruise data may be downloaded via the web.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='common_arguments_and_specifications'><title>COMMON ARGUMENTS AND SPECIFICATIONS</title>
<para>All options marked with an asterisk (*) are common GMT command-line options.  Their full syntax as well as
how to specify pens, pattern fills, colors, and fonts can be found in the <emphasis remap='B'>gmt</emphasis> man page.
Note: No space is allowed between the option flag and the associated arguments.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='required_arguments'><title>REQUIRED ARGUMENTS</title>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='I'>NGDC-ids</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Can be one or more of five kinds of specifiers:
<!-- .br -->
1) 8-character NGDC IDs, e.g., 01010083, JA010010etc., etc.
<!-- .br -->
2) 2-character &lt;agency&gt; codes which will return all cruises from each agency.
<!-- .br -->
3) 4-character &lt;agency&gt;&lt;vessel&gt; codes, which will return all cruises from those vessels.
<!-- .br -->
4) =&lt;list&gt;, where &lt;list&gt; is a table with NGDC IDs, one per line.
<!-- .br -->
5) If nothing is specified we return all cruises in the data base.
<!-- .br -->
(See mgd77info <option>-L</option> for agency and vessel codes).
The ".mgd77" or ".nc" extensions will automatically be appended, if needed (use <option>-I</option>
to ignore certain file types).  Cruise files will be looked for first in the current directory
and second in all directories listed in <emphasis remap='B'>$MGD77_HOME</emphasis>/mgd77_paths.txt [If <emphasis remap='B'>$MGD77_HOME</emphasis>
is not set it will default to <emphasis remap='B'>$GMT_SHAREDIR</emphasis>/mgd77].</para>
<!-- .br -->
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='optional_arguments'><title>OPTIONAL ARGUMENTS</title>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-A</option><replaceable>fieldabbrev</replaceable>,<emphasis remap='I'>scale</emphasis>,<emphasis remap='I'>offset</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Apply scale factor and DC adjustment to specified data field. Allows adjustment of cruise data prior
to along-track analysis. CAUTION: data must be thoroughly examined before applying these global data
adjustments. May not be used for multiple cruises.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-C</option><replaceable>maxspd</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Set maximum ship speed in m/s, or knots with <option>-N</option> option. Ship speeds exceeding 10 m/s (~20 knots)
are flagged as excessive by default.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-D</option><replaceable>d</replaceable>|<emphasis remap='B'>e</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>E</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>f</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>l</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>m</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>s</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>v</emphasis>[<emphasis remap='I'>r</emphasis>]</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Suppress default warning output and only dump cruise data row-by-row such as values, gradients,
grid-cruise differences, E77 error summaries for each record, re-created MGD77 records
or sniffer limits. Append r to include all records (default omits records where navigation errors were detected).</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Dd</option>
output differences between cruise and grid data. Requires <option>-G</option> option. Output columns include:</para> 
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='I'>lat lon dist cruiseZ gridZ diff [cruiseZ2 gridZ2 diff2 ...]</emphasis></para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>Note: grid values are subtracted from cruise data so a positive difference implies cruise &gt; grid.
For multiple grid comparison, <emphasis remap='I'>cruiseZ gridZ diff</emphasis> are repeated for each grid comparison in command line order.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-De</option>
output E77 error classification format. Error output is divided into (1) a header containing
information globally applicable to the cruise and (2) individual error records summarizing all
errors encountered in each cruise record. mgd77sniffer writes E77 directly to &lt;ngdc_id.e77&gt;
file handle. See <emphasis remap='B'>E77 ERROR FORMAT</emphasis> below for additional details.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-DE</option>
Same as <option>-De</option> but no regression tests will be carried out.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Df</option>
output delta Z (change in geophysical field) column and delta S (change in distance) for each
geophysical field. Distance between observations often differ for different fields depending
on instrument sampling rate, so ds is included for each geophysical observation. Output
columns include:</para> 
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='I'>d[twt] ds d[depth] ds d[mtf1] ds d[mtf2] ds d[mag] ds d[diur] ds d[msd] ds d[gobs] ds d[eot] ds d[faa] ds</emphasis></para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Dl</option>
display mgd77sniffer limits. Customize this output to create a custom limits file for 
the <option>-L</option> option. No additional arguments are required. Output columns include:</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='I'>fieldabbrev min max maxSlope maxArea</emphasis></para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Dm</option>
output MGD77 format records in Y2K-compliant MGD77 format</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Dn</option>
output distance to coast for each record. Requires <option>-Gnav</option> or <option>-gnav</option> option. Output columns include:</para> 
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='I'>lat lon dist distToCoast</emphasis></para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Ds</option>
output calculated gradients for speed and geophysical fields. Gradients correspond to the gradient type
selected in the <option>-S</option> option (spatial derivatives by default). Output columns include:</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='I'>speed d[twt] d[depth] d[mtf1] d[mtf2] d[mag] d[diur] d[msd] d[gobs] d[eot] d[faa]</emphasis></para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>See <emphasis remap='B'>MGD77 FIELD INFO</emphasis> below for field and abbreviations descriptions.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Dv</option>
display values for the twelve position and geophysical fields for each MGD77 data record (in this order):</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='I'>lat lon twt depth mtf1 mtf2 mag diur msens gobs eot faa</emphasis></para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>See below for <emphasis remap='B'>MGD77 FIELD INFO</emphasis>.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-g</option><replaceable>fieldabbrev</replaceable>,<emphasis remap='I'>imggrid</emphasis>,<emphasis remap='I'>scale</emphasis>,<emphasis remap='I'>mode</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Compare cruise data to the specified grid in Sandwell/Smith Mercator format. Requires a valid MGD77 field abbreviation (see 
<emphasis remap='B'>MGD77 FIELD INFO</emphasis> below) followed by a comma, the path (if not in current directory)
and grid filename, a scale to multiply the data (1 or 0.1), and mode which stand for the following:
(0) Img files with no constraint code, returns data at all points, (1) Img file with constraints coded,
return data at all points, (2) Img file with constraints coded, return data only at constrained points
and NaN elsewhere, and (3) Img file with constraints coded, return 1 at constraints and 0 elsewhere.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-G</option><replaceable>fieldabbrev</replaceable>,<emphasis remap='I'>grid</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Compare cruise data to the specified grid. Requires a valid MGD77 field abbreviation (see 
<emphasis remap='B'>MGD77 FIELD INFO</emphasis> below) followed by a comma, then the path (if not in current directory)
and grid filename. Multiple grid comparison is supported by using separate <option>-g</option> or <option>-G</option> calls for each 
grid. See <emphasis remap='B'>GRID FILE INFO</emphasis> below.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>Grid comparison activates several additional error checks. (1) Re-weighted Least Squares 
Regression of ship versus grid data determines slope and DC shift, which when differing
from expected 1 and 0, respectively, may indicate incorrectly scaled ship data, including
incorrect units or instrument drift as well as erroneous gravity tie-in. (2) Accumulated ship
grid offsets are computed along-track and excessive offsets are flagged according to <emphasis remap='I'>maxArea</emphasis>
threshold (use <option>-L</option> option to adjust <emphasis remap='I'>maxArea</emphasis>). Warning: predicted bathymetry grids are
constrained by cruise data so grids and cruise data are not always independent. Comparison of
cruise bathymetry with predicted bathymetry grids also activates a "navigation crossing over land"
check.</para>
<!-- .br -->

  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-H</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>(with <option>-G</option>|<emphasis remap='B'>g</emphasis> only) disable (or force) decimation during RLS analysis of ship and gridded data.
By default mgd77sniffer analyses both the full and decimated data sets then reports RLS statistics for the
higher correlation regression.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Hb</option> analyze both (default), report better of two.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Hd</option> to disable data decimation (equivalent to -H with no argument).</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><option>-Hf</option> to force data decimation.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-I</option><replaceable>fieldabbrev</replaceable>,<emphasis remap='I'>rec1</emphasis>,<emphasis remap='I'>recN</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Append a field abbreviation and the first and last record in a range of records that should
be flagged as bad (and set to NaN prior to the analysis). Repeat as many times as needed.
May not be used for multiple cruises.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-K</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Reverse navigation quality flags (good to bad and vice versa). May be necessary when a
majority of navigation fixes are erroneously flagged bad, which can happen when a cruise's
first navigation fix is extremely erroneous. Caution! This will affect sniffer output and
should only be attempted after careful manual navigation review.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-L</option><replaceable>custom-limits-file</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Override mgd77sniffer default error detection limits. Supply path and filename to
the custom limits file. Rows not beginning with a valid MGD77 field abbreviation are
ignored. Field abbreviations are listed below in exact form under MGD77 FIELD INFO.
Multiple field limits may be modified using one default file, one field per line.
Field min, max, max slope and max area may be changed for each field. Max slope
pertains to the gradient type selected using the <option>-S</option> option. Max area is used by the
<option>-G</option> option as the threshold for flagging excessive offsets from the specified grid.
Dump defaults <option>-Dl</option> to view syntax or to quickly create an editable custom limits file.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>Example custom default file contents (see below for units):</para>
<!-- .br -->

<table pgwide='0' frame='none'>
  <caption>-</caption>
  <tgroup cols='5' align='center'>
    <colspec colname='c1'/>
    <colspec colname='c2'/>
    <colspec colname='c3'/>
    <colspec colname='c4'/>
    <colspec colname='c5'/>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>\('## abbrev</entry>
        <entry align='left'>min</entry>
        <entry align='left'>max</entry>
        <entry align='left'>maxSlope</entry>
        <entry align='left'>maxArea\"'</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>twt</entry>
        <entry align='left'>0</entry>
        <entry align='left'>15</entry>
        <entry align='left'>1</entry>
        <entry align='left'>0</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>depth</entry>
        <entry align='left'>0</entry>
        <entry align='left'>11000</entry>
        <entry align='left'>500</entry>
        <entry align='left'>5000</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>mag</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-800</entry>
        <entry align='left'>800</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>faa</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-300</entry>
        <entry align='left'>300</entry>
        <entry align='left'>100</entry>
        <entry align='left'>2500</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</table>



<para>Use a dash '-' to retain a default limit.
Hint: to test your custom limits, try: mgd77sniffer <option>-Dl</option> <option>-L</option>&lt;yourlimitsfile&gt;</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-N</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Use nautical units.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-P</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Flag regression statistics that are outside the specified confidence level.
(i.e., -P5 flags coefficients m, b, rms, and r that fall outside 95%.)</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-R</option><replaceable>west</replaceable>/<emphasis remap='I'>east</emphasis>/<emphasis remap='I'>south</emphasis>/<emphasis remap='I'>north</emphasis>[/<emphasis remap='I'>zmin</emphasis>/<emphasis remap='I'>zmax</emphasis>][<emphasis remap='B'>r</emphasis>]</term>
  <listitem>
<para><emphasis remap='I'>west</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>east</emphasis>, <emphasis remap='I'>south</emphasis>, and <emphasis remap='I'>north</emphasis> specify the region of interest, and you may specify them
in decimal degrees or in [+-]dd:mm[:ss.xxx][W|E|S|N] format.  Append <emphasis remap='B'>r</emphasis> if lower left and upper right
map coordinates are given instead of w/e/s/n.  The two shorthands <option>-Rg</option> and <option>-Rd</option> stand for global domain
(0/360 and -180/+180 in longitude respectively, with -90/+90 in latitude). Alternatively, specify the name
of an existing grid file and the <option>-R</option> settings (and grid spacing, if applicable) are copied from the grid.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-S</option><replaceable>d</replaceable>|<emphasis remap='B'>s</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>t</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify gradient type for along-track excessive slope checking.
<!-- .br -->
<option>-Sd</option>
Calculate change in z values along track (dz). Output is given in geophysical units,
e.g. mGal.
<!-- .br -->
<option>-Ss</option>
Calculate spatial gradients (dz/ds). Output is given in geophysical units per km along the
survey track, e.g. mGal/km.
<!-- .br -->
<option>-St</option> Calculate time gradients (dz/dt)  [default]. Output is given in geophysical units
per second along the survey track, e.g. mGal/sec.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-T</option><replaceable>gap</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Adjusts mgd77sniffer gap handling. By default, data gaps greater than 5 km are skipped. Set to
zero to de-activate gap skipping.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-W</option><replaceable>c</replaceable>|<emphasis remap='B'>g</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>o</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>s</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>t</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>v</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>x</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Print out only certain warning types for verbose error messages. Comma delimit any combination of
<emphasis remap='B'>c|g|o|s|t|v|x</emphasis>: where (<emphasis remap='B'>c</emphasis>) type code warnings, (<emphasis remap='B'>g</emphasis>)radient out of range, (<emphasis remap='B'>o</emphasis>)ffsets
from grid (requires <option>-G</option>|<emphasis remap='B'>g</emphasis>), (<emphasis remap='B'>s</emphasis>)peed out of range, (<emphasis remap='B'>t</emphasis>)ime warnings, (<emphasis remap='B'>v</emphasis>)alue out of 
range, (<emphasis remap='B'>x</emphasis>) warning summaries. By default ALL warning messages are printed.Not compatible with any
<option>-D</option> options.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-V</option><replaceable>level</replaceable> (*)</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Select verbosity level [1].</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-bo</option><replaceable>ncol</replaceable>[<emphasis remap='B'>t</emphasis>]</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Output binary data for <option>-D</option>d|f|s|v option.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-n</option>[<emphasis remap='B'>b</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>c</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>l</emphasis>|<emphasis remap='B'>n</emphasis>][<option>+a</option>][<emphasis remap='B'>+b</emphasis><emphasis remap='I'>BC</emphasis>][<emphasis remap='B'>+t</emphasis><emphasis remap='I'>threshold</emphasis>] (*)</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Select interpolation mode for grids.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-^</option> (*)</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Print a short message about the syntax of the command, then exits.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-?</option> (*)</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Print a full usage (help) message, including the explanation of options, then exits.</para>

  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='mgd77_field_info'><title>MGD77 FIELD INFO</title>

<table pgwide='0' frame='none'>
  <caption/>
  <title></title>
  <tgroup cols='3' align='center'>
    <colspec colname='c1'/>
    <colspec colname='c2'/>
    <colspec colname='c3'/>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'><emphasis remap='I'>Field</emphasis></entry>
        <entry align='left'><emphasis remap='I'>Abbreviation</emphasis></entry>
        <entry align='left'><emphasis remap='I'>Units</emphasis></entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Two-way</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Travel</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Time</entry>
        <entry align='left'>twt</entry>
        <entry align='left'>sec</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Corrected</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Depth</entry>
        <entry align='left'>depth</entry>
        <entry align='left'>m</entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Mag</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Total</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Field1</entry>
        <entry align='left'>mtf1</entry>
        <entry align='left'>nT</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Mag</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Total</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Field2</entry>
        <entry align='left'>mtf2</entry>
        <entry align='left'>nT</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Residual</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Magnetic</entry>
        <entry align='left'>mag</entry>
        <entry align='left'>nT</entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Diurnal</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Correction</entry>
        <entry align='left'>diur</entry>
        <entry align='left'>nT</entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Mag</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Sensor</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Depth/Alt</entry>
        <entry align='left'>msens</entry>
        <entry align='left'>m</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Observed</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Gravity</entry>
        <entry align='left'>gobs</entry>
        <entry align='left'>mGal</entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Eotvos</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Correction</entry>
        <entry align='left'>eot</entry>
        <entry align='left'>mGal</entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>Free</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Air</entry>
        <entry align='left'>Anomaly</entry>
        <entry align='left'>faa</entry>
        <entry align='left'>mGal</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</table>




</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='grid_file_info'><title>GRID FILE INFO</title>
<para>For <option>-g</option> the grids must be in the format used by Sandwell &amp; Smith, which is a spherical Mercator 2-byte grid with no header.
For <option>-G</option> the grid files can be of any grid type supported by GMT and therefore must contain a GMT header. 
A correctly formatted *.i2 grid file can be generated using grdraster as shown below.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>gmtset GRIDFILE_SHORTHAND TRUE</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>Create/edit .gmt_io file to include the following rows:</para>
<!-- .br -->

<table pgwide='0' frame='none'>
  <caption/>
  <title></title>
  <tgroup cols='5' align='center'>
    <colspec colname='c1'/>
    <colspec colname='c2'/>
    <colspec colname='c3'/>
    <colspec colname='c4'/>
    <colspec colname='c5'/>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>\('## GMT I/O shorthand file\"'</entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
        <entry align='left'></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>\('## suffix</entry>
        <entry align='left'>format_id</entry>
        <entry align='left'>scale</entry>
        <entry align='left'>offset</entry>
        <entry align='left'>NaN\"'</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>grd</entry>
        <entry align='left'>0</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align='left'>i2</entry>
        <entry align='left'>2</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-</entry>
        <entry align='left'>-</entry>
        <entry align='left'>32767</entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</table>



<para>grdraster 1 -R0/359:55/-90/90 -Getopo5_hdr.i2</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>The new grid, etopo5_hdr.i2 in this example, contains a GMT header and can be used in
the <option>-G</option> option to compare cruise depth with grid values.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='e77_error_format'><title>E77 ERROR FORMAT</title>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>Header</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Information pertaining to an entire cruise, such as NGDC and survey institution identification codes,
cruise examination time, two-way travel time corrector information, data precision warnings, as well as 
systematic scales, DC shifts and correlation coefficients from global grid comparisons are reported as
E77 header information.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='B'>Sample</emphasis>
<!-- .br -->
\('## Cruise 08010039 ID 74010908 MGD77 FILE VERSION: 19801230 N_RECS: 3066\"'
<!-- .br -->
\('## Examined: Wed Oct  3 16:30:13 2007 by mtchandl\"'
<!-- .br -->
\('## Arguments:  -De -Gdepth,/data/GRIDS/etopo5_hdr.i2\"'
<!-- .br -->
N Errata table verification status
<!-- .br -->
\('## mgd77manage applies corrections if the errata table is verified (toggle 'N' above to 'Y' after review)\"'
<!-- .br -->
\('## For instructions on E77 format and usage, see http://gmt.soest.hawaii.edu/mgd77/errata.php\"'
<!-- .br -->
\('## Verified by:\"'
<!-- .br -->
\('## Comments:\"'
<!-- .br -->
\('## Errata: Header\"'
<!-- .br -->
Y-E-08010039-H13-02: Invalid Magnetics Sampling Rate: (99) [  ]
<!-- .br -->
Y-W-08010039-H13-10: Survey year (1975) outside magnetic reference field IGRF 1965 time range (1965-1970)
<!-- .br -->
Y-I-08010039-depth-00: RLS m: 1.00053 b: 0 rms: 127.851 r: 0.973422 significant: 1 decimation: 0
<!-- .br -->
Y-W-08010039-twt-09: More recent bathymetry correction table available
<!-- .br -->
Y-W-08010039-mtf1-10: Integer precision
<!-- .br -->
Y-W-08010039-mag-10: Integer precision</para>
<!-- .br -->

  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>Error Record</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Individual error records have strict format. Included is a time or distance column followed by record number,
a formatted error code string, and finally a verbose description of errors detected in the record. Three error
classes are encoded into the error code string with different alphabetic characters representing unique error
types. See below for error code format description.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='B'>Format</emphasis>
<!-- .br -->
&lt;time/distance&gt; &lt;record number&gt; &lt;error code string&gt; &lt;description&gt;</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='B'>Sample</emphasis>
<!-- .br -->
\('## Errata: Data\"'
<!-- .br -->
Y	08010039	1975-05-10T22:16:05.88	74	C-0-0	 NAV: excessive speed</para>
<!-- .br -->

  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>Error Code Description</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Each of the three error classes is separated by a dash '-' and described by a
combination of alphabetic characters or 0 signifying no detected problems.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>Error classes: NAV-VAL-GRAD</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><emphasis remap='B'>Error Class Descriptions</emphasis>
<!-- .br -->
NAV (navigation):
<!-- .br -->
0 - fine
<!-- .br -->
A - time out of range
<!-- .br -->
B - time decreasing
<!-- .br -->
C - excessive speed
<!-- .br -->
D - above sea level
<!-- .br -->
E - lat undefined
<!-- .br -->
F - lon undefined</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>VAL (value):
<!-- .br -->
0 - fine
<!-- .br -->
K - twt invalid
<!-- .br -->
L - depth invalid
<!-- .br -->
O - mtf1 invalid
<!-- .br -->
etc.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>GRAD (gradient):
<!-- .br -->
0 - fine
<!-- .br -->
K - d[twt] excessive
<!-- .br -->
L - d[depth] excessive
<!-- .br -->
O - d[mtf1] excessive
<!-- .br -->
etc.</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>The NAV error class has unique cases while VAL and GRAD classes are
described by alphabetic characters for each of the 24 numeric fields in MGD77 format order.</para>

<para>  MGD77 bit-pattern w/ E77 alpha characters
<!-- .br -->
|-------------------------------------------------|----------|
<!-- .br -->
| X W V U T S R Q P O N M L K J I H G F E D C B A | E77 Code |
<!-- .br -->
| - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - | - - - - -|
<!-- .br -->
| n f e g m d m m m m b b d t p l l m h d m y t d | F  I     |
<!-- .br -->
| q a o o s i s a t t t c e w t o a i o a o e z r | i  D     |
<!-- .br -->
| c a t b d u e g f f c c p t c n t n u y n a   t | e        |
<!-- .br -->
|       s   r n   2 1     t           r   t r     | l        |
<!-- .br -->
|             s           h               h       | d        |
<!-- .br -->
| - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - | - - - - -|
<!-- .br -->
| 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 | Bit place|
<!-- .br -->
| - G C G C C - G G G - - G G - - - T T T T T - - | Bit type |
<!-- .br -->
|-------------------------------------------------|----------|
<!-- .br -->
  Bit types: (G)eophysical, (C)orrection, (T)ime</para> 
<!-- .br -->

  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='examples'><title>EXAMPLES</title>
<para>To scan for excessive values or gradients, try</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><command>mgd77sniffer</command> 08010001</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>To dump cruise gradients, try</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><command>mgd77sniffer</command> 08010001 -Ds</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para>To compare cruise depth with ETOPO5 bathymetry and gravity with Sandwell/Smith 2 min gravity version 11, try</para>
<!-- .br -->

<para><command>mgd77sniffer</command> 08010001 <option>-G</option>depth,/data/GRIDS/etopo5_hdr.i2 <option>-g</option>faa,/data/GRIDS/grav.11.2.img,0.1,1</para>
<!-- .br -->

</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para><citerefentry><refentrytitle>mgd77list</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>mgd77track</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>x2sys_init</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry></para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='references'><title>REFERENCES</title>
<para>Wessel, P., W. H. F. Smith, R. Scharroo, and J. Luis,  2011, The Generic Mapping Tools (GMT) version
5.0.0b Technical Reference &amp; Cookbook, SOEST/NOAA.
<!-- .br -->
Wessel, P., and W. H. F. Smith, 1998, New, Improved Version of Generic Mapping
Tools Released, EOS Trans., AGU, 79 (47), p. 579.
<!-- .br -->
Wessel, P., and W. H. F. Smith, 1995, New Version of the Generic Mapping Tools
Released, EOS Trans., AGU, 76 (33), p. 329.
<!-- .br -->
Wessel, P., and W. H. F. Smith, 1995, New Version of the Generic Mapping Tools
Released, http://www.agu.org/eos_elec/95154e.html, Copyright 1995 by the
American Geophysical Union.
<!-- .br -->
Wessel, P., and W. H. F. Smith, 1991, Free Software Helps Map and Display Data,
EOS Trans., AGU, 72 (41), p. 441.
<!-- .br -->
The Marine Geophysical Data Exchange Format - MGD77, see
<emphasis remap='I'>http://www.ngdc.noaa.gov/mgg/dat/geodas/docs/mgd77.txt</emphasis>.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

